in this video we're going to continue
using Clifford algebras to generalize
the complex numbers and quaternions to
spin groups which help us do rotations
in any dimension
the unit length complex numbers are
actually the group Spin 2 because they
give us rotations in 2D space the unit
length quaternions are actually the
group spin three because they give us
rotations in 3D space the spin and group
is the generalization of these that
gives us rotations in n-dimensional
space
we'll Define spin groups using Clifford
algebras which are algebras where the
basis vectors Square two plus one or -1
and where orthogonal vectors
anti-commute with each other
it turns out that it's better to view
the complex I as the Clifford bi-vector
Sigma X Sigma Y which represents a
rotation in the X Y plane
the unit quaternions are also better
represented as bi-vectors instead of
rotating around axis I we should think
of rotating in the YZ plane and instead
of axis J we think of the ZX plane and
instead of axis K we think of the X Y
plane
the bi-vectors also multiply together to
give us the standard quaternion
multiplication rules because of the
anti-commutative property
since bi-vectors and Clifford algebras
always give us rotations we can extend
this pattern to work in any Dimension n
where the bi-vector sigma a sigma B
gives us a rotation in the a b plane
this is how we Define the spin and group
we can also generalize this to space
time the group spin 1 3 gives us both
rotations and lorentz boosts in one time
Dimension and three space dimensions
its generalization is spin PQ for
rotations and boosts in P time
dimensions and Q space dimensions
in this video I'm going to show how
Clifford algebras can be used to do
Reflections and rotations on vectors in
any Dimension this explains why Clifford
algebras are also called geometric
algebras because they allow us to easily
perform geometric operations on vectors
some of this video's content was already
covered in video number six when I
introduced the Pauli matrices and Paulie
vectors but that video relied on
matrices to do rotations this video will
involve no matrices and only use
abstract symbols from the Clifford
algebras to do geometric operations
before we start I'd like to go over some
names we give to various members of
Clifford algebras just so we're on the
same page when I use them later
the standard building block in Clifford
algebras is the vector which belongs to
some Vector space V
ectors combined together with the wedge
product give us bi-vectors Tri vectors
or general K vectors also called
k-blades
the grade of a k Vector refers to how
many vectors appear in the wedge product
an arbitrary sum of K vectors is called
a multi-vector
when we have a Clifford product of
vectors we call this averser note that
the Clifford product of two vectors is
not the same thing as a bi-vector since
the Clifford product gives us the sum of
a scalar and a bi-vector
the Clifford product and wedge product
are only the same if the two vectors are
orthogonal and the dot product part goes
to zero
with this out of the way let's get
started with learning about rotations
and Reflections in Clifford algebras
to start let's look at cl30 the Clifford
algebra in 3D space with three
orthonormal basis vectors that square
two plus one which are Sigma X Sigma Y
and sigma Z and when we multiply two
different orthogonal basis vectors
together we can switch their order if we
include a negative sign since
multiplication of orthogonal vectors is
anti-commutative
let's start with performing Vector
reflections
we reflect vectors by performing
negative conjugation on them using the
vector we want to reflect along
let's see how this works if we want to
reflect a vector along the z-axis this
means we leave the X and Y components
the same but change the sign of the Z
component so this is like if the plane
perpendicular to Z the X Y plane is a
mirror that we're reflecting in
reflection of a vector v along the Z
direction is done using negative
conjugation by Zed which means we
multiply by Sigma Z on the left and
sigma Z inverse on the right and include
a negative sign in front
for example reflecting Sigma X along
Sigma Z looks like this the colors don't
mean anything here they're just to make
the formula more readable
since Sigma Z multiplied by itself gives
plus one this means Sigma Z is its own
inverse so we can just drop the inverse
operation after swapping we get an
additional negative sign in front which
cancels with the first negative sign
also Sigma Z squared gives us plus one
so we get Sigma X as a result
it makes sense that Sigma X is unchanged
when we reflect it in this mirror
associated with Sigma Z
the same is true for reflecting Sigma y
along the z-axis
but if we want to reflect Sigma Z along
the z-axis sigma Z immediately cancels
with Sigma Z inverse and so we get
Negative Sigma Z
so the sigma Z basis Vector has been
reflected as expected
if we take a general vector v which is a
linear combination of Sigma X Sigma Y
and sigma Z and reflect it along Z with
a negative conjugation the X and Y parts
are left unchanged but the Z part is
reflected and gets a negative sign as
expected
now when we're doing reflection along a
unit Vector that squares 2 1 such as
Sigma Z its inverse is not required in
the conjugation formula
however if we reflect along a vector U
which doesn't have unit length we need
to properly calculate the inverse
we know U times U equals the squared
length of U we can multiply on both
sides by U inverse cancel U and U
inverse and then divide by the squared
length so U inverse equals U divided by
the squared length of U
for example if we reflect along 5 Sigma
Z its squared length is 5 squared so the
inverse is 5 Sigma Z over five squared
in the negative conjugation each factor
of one over five serves to normalize the
vectors in the reflection formula if
they are not already normalized
so we get the same reflection formula as
if we had just reflected along a unit
length Sigma Z vector
we can prove this reflection formula
works for any invertible Vector U
we break V into portions parallel to U
and perpendicular to you then distribute
the parallel portion of V can be written
as a scaled version of U using a scale
factor k
and the perpendicular part of V will
anti-commute with u so we can swap their
order and change the sign
U and U inverse combine to one here and
here and we can rewrite K times U as the
parallel portion of V
the result is V where the portion
parallel to U is reflected with a minus
sign and the perpendicular part is
unchanged as expected
so this negative conjugation formula
breaks a vector v up into Parts parallel
to U and perpendicular to you and it
only reflects the part parallel to you
we can also confirm that this reflection
formula keeps the length of V unchanged
if we take V times V and then reflect
both V's the negative signs cancel and
the inner uu inverse cancel V times V
gives the squared length of V which is a
scalar that can be moved here so that U
and U inverse cancel so the squared
length of V is unchanged by reflection
now let's look at space time which has
the Clifford algebra cl13 this has one
dimension of time and three dimensions
of space given by the orthonormal basis
vectors gamma T gamma X gamma Y and
Gamma Z
according to the plus minus minus minus
metric the time basis Vector squares two
plus one and each of the space basis
vectors Square two minus one and the
basis vectors anti-commute with each
other
we could also choose to work in cl31 if
we wanted which uses the mostly plus
metric convention but for this video I'm
going to work in cl13 which has the
mostly minus convention
let's review some of the basics of
special relativity the lengths of
space-time vectors are measured using
the space-time interval formula given
here
as an exercise you can check that we get
this formula when we square a space-time
vector and that the Clifford algebra
symbols give us all the correct signs
looking at a space-time diagram the
time-like vectors that point to the
future or the past have positive squared
lengths
space-like vectors that point in spatial
directions have negative squared lengths
and lights like vectors that point along
light beams have zero squared lengths
it's very important to remember what
orthogonality looks like in space time
in ordinary space two vectors are
orthogonal if they meet at right angles
in space time a time-like vector and a
space-like vector are orthogonal if they
make equal angles with a beam of light
this affects how Reflections work in
space-time
in ordinary space a reflection Vector
defines a mirror that is orthogonal to
it when we reflect a vector in the
mirror the initial and reflected vectors
form equal circular angles with the
mirror
in space-time a reflection Vector also
defines a mirror that is orthogonal to
it but recall orthogonality means
forming equal angles with a light beam
so the mirror looks like this
when we reflect a vector in the mirror
the initial and final vectors form equal
hyperbolic angles with the mirror
so this is a little more complicated
than physical space but the basic idea
is the same
the Reflections in space time are done
exactly as before with negative
conjugation however note that the
inverse operation on the right is always
required
if we reflect with a space like vector
its squared length is negative and this
negative sign is important to keep track
of in the reflection formula
gamma X for example is a space like
vector this means that the inverse of
gamma X is actually negative gamma X
since gamma X squares to negative one
this extra minus sign in the inverse is
important to keep track of
if we try to do a reflection this extra
minus sign will cancel out with the
minus sign we get from squaring gamma X
ensuring that our result has the correct
sign
also some vectors in space time such as
gamma t plus gamma Z Square to zero
these are the light like vectors which
point along the paths of light beams in
space time
because their squared length is zero
lights like vectors have no inverse and
so we cannot use them to reflect along
four reflections
you can think of a light-like vector as
existing at an infinite hyperbolic angle
so we can't use it to measure hyperbolic
reflection angles with our initial and
final vectors
so reflections of vectors in physical
space and space time both use the same
negative conjugation formula
this negative conjugation Works in all
Clifford algebras of any Dimension as
well not just 3D space or 4D space-time
now let's look into doing rotations in
physical space with cl30
a rotation can be thought of as a pair
of Reflections for example if we take
this flag and reflect it in this mirror
then take the result and reflect it in
this mirror we end up with a rotation of
the original flag
so if we want to rotate something all we
need to do is do a pair of reflections
also notice that the angle of the flag's
rotation is twice the angle between the
two mirrors that we used
so if we want to do a rotation by some
angle Theta all we need to do is pick
two reflection vectors that are at an
angle of theta over two apart
let's say we want to do a rotation by
angle Theta in the X Y plane first we
reflect along the x-axis with Sigma X
then we reflect along a unit Vector Tau
which forms an angle of theta over two
with Sigma X
in other words Tau equals cosine Theta
over 2 Sigma X Plus sine Theta over 2
Sigma y
so let's see what our rotation formula
looks like on a vector v
first we reflect along Sigma X then we
reflect along Tau the two negative signs
in the double reflection cancel out also
it's a rule in algebra that the inverse
of a product is the product of the
inverses written in the opposite order
this causes the terms in their inverses
to cancel out one by one
so we can rewrite Sigma X inverse times
Tau inverse as the inverse of Tau times
Sigma X
note that our rotation formula is also a
conjugation formula with a product of
vectors on the left and the inverse of
that product of vectors on the right
we'll call this product of vectors
averser which is a word we'll talk more
about later
the angle between the two vectors in the
verser is half of the rotation angle
so it's as if each verser does a
rotation of theta over two and they
combine to do a rotation of theta
now let's plug in our definition of Tau
into the rotation formula
we can distribute the sigma X
recall that Sigma x squared equals plus
one so we get this
as a final step I'm going to reverse the
order of the sigmas and introduce a
negative sign so that it reads negative
Sigma x times Sigma y this reminds us
that the rotation is in the orientation
that brings the positive x-axis towards
the positive y-axis
now let's look at what we have so far we
know rotations are done using
conjugation with a product of a pair of
vectors and this pair of vectors is
sometimes called averser
the verser can be written using a pair
of vectors like this or in expanded form
using cosines and Sines
note that this verser is not a bi-vector
in general a bi-vector is given by the
wedge product of two vectors but the
verser is given by the Clifford product
of two vectors which has a DOT product
part that results in a scalar and a
wedge product part which results in a
bi-vector
now what is the inverse of this verser
recall that we can write the inverse of
a product as the product of inverses in
the opposite order recall Sigma X and
Tau are not always orthogonal so we
cannot swap them in exchange for a
negative sign
however since Sigma X and Tau are both
unit vectors that square two plus one
they are their own inverses
so in this special case of unit vectors
the inverse of the verser involves just
swapping the order of the vectors
we can also apply this logic to our
formula with Sines and cosines we get
the inverse just by swapping the order
of the sigmas
since Sigma X and sigma y are orthogonal
we can swap them in exchange for a
negative sign if we want
Sigma x times Sigma y also squares 2
negative one so it's similar to The
Complex I and the reversal operation is
a bit like taking the complex conjugate
in the special case where the verser is
made up of unit vectors we can replace
the inverse operation with a reversal
operation which is often written as a
tilde or a dagger the dagger taking
inspiration from the hermitian conjugate
which is known to reverse the order of
Pauli matrices
however what if we used averser that is
not made of unit vectors such as 5 Sigma
x times Tau
the inverse in this case is not just the
reverse we need to include additional
numerical factors because the vectors
don't have length one
the inverse ends up being the reverse
Tau times 5 Sigma X all over 5 squared
which is the squared magnitude of 5
Sigma X
just like we saw with Reflections each
factor of one over five will normalize
the vectors on either side making the
formula the same as if we rotated using
averser made up of only unit vectors
now let's explicitly check that this
formula actually works
we can distribute V over the left
brackets
since cosine is just a scalar we can
bring V to the other side for free
for the sine term things are more
complicated depending on whether or not
V is in the plane of rotation
if V is not in the plane of rotation for
example V equals Sigma Z then we do two
flips here picking up two negative signs
that cancel out and the result is
unchanged
in other words if V is not in the plane
of rotation we can move V to the other
side of this expression without any
changes
these two expressions are inverses of
each other and so they cancel out
leaving V unchanged
so if the vector v is outside the plane
of rotation this rotation formula does
not affect it
however if V is in the plane of rotation
for example Sigma X then we only pick up
one negative sign while doing the
swapping since swapping a basis Vector
with itself does nothing in this case we
do end up with a sign change
we can Factor Sigma X out in front and
as we showed before taking the inverse
of this expression is the same thing as
changing the sign in front of the sigmas
so now instead of the vector being
unchanged we have the vector times this
product
Distributing we get cosine squared plus
two cosine sine times the X Y by Vector
plus sine squared with the X Y by Vector
squared as discussed before the X Y by
Vector squares 2 negative one leaving us
with negative sine squared
the result involves the double angle
formula for cosine and the double angle
formula for sine so the angles of theta
over two get doubled to Theta
after we distribute the sigma X the
cosine term gets Sigma X and the sine
term gets Sigma x squared which goes to
1. leaving it with only Sigma y
this results in the original Vector
rotated by an angle Theta as expected
if a vector has Parts both inside and
outside the plane of rotation only the
part inside the plane of rotation will
be affected by this formula
so in conclusion this double-sided
operation will rotate vectors within the
plane of rotation and ignore vectors
outside the plane of rotation as
expected
we can get similar formulas for the YZ
and ZX planes but remember you can
always rotate in any arbitrary plane of
your choice just pick two vectors in
that plane A and B and ensure they are
separated by an angle of theta over two
you can then double reflect along each
of these vectors and this is equivalent
to doing a rotation by an angle Theta in
the a b plane
now let's look back at our formula for
rotating in the X Y plane this
expression here has a lot in common with
Euler's formula which says that e to the
I times an angle equals cosine plus I
times sine
the reason that this is true is due to
the fact that I squares 2 negative one
it turns out that Sigma x times Sigma y
also squares 2 negative one so these
formulas are very similar and it turns
out that we can write this expression as
e to the sigma X Sigma y Theta over two
let's recall the Taylor series of e to
the X we get an infinite polynomial in X
with factorials in the denominator
if we do e to the I Theta then the first
term with the zero power goes to one the
first Power gets an i out in front the
second power gives us I squared which is
negative one the third power gives us I
cubed which is I squared times I which
is just negative I and the fourth power
gives us I squared twice which is
negative one times negative one equals
positive one
this pattern of one I negative one
negative I repeats forever
if we separate the terms without I from
the terms with I the series Without I is
the Taylor series for cosine and the
series with I is the Taylor series first
sign
this is the proof of Euler's formula
if we do this exercise again but with
replacing I with Sigma x times Sigma y
it works out the exact same way since
the bi Vector Sigma X Sigma y also
squares 2 negative one
so Euler's formula doesn't just work for
I it works for any symbol that squares
to negative one
also note that if we use a negative
angle in this formula the cosine term is
unchanged since cosine is symmetric the
cosine of an angle and its negative give
the same result
the sine term however can have the
negative sign moved out in front since
sine is an anti-symmetric function
so we can replace these formulas with a
negative exponential and a positive
exponential involving the bi-vector
sigma X Sigma y
this exponential version of the formula
works for rotating in any plane given by
two sigmas
more generally the rotation formula can
be performed with any general unit by
Vector B that squares 2 negative one
recall a bifector represents an oriented
plane given by the wedge product of two
vectors
the bifectors orientation in space gives
the plane and direction of rotation
the Theta over 2 scales the size of the
bi-vector to the size required for
rotating by an angle Theta
one way to get to the required bi-vector
in 3D is to write out a unit Vector for
the axis of rotation and then replace
the basis vectors with the corresponding
orthogonal bi-vector planes
after being exponentiated the bifector
becomes averser and this is what
performs the rotation
now you might be confused about this
double-sided transformation if we want
to rotate a complex number A Plus IB we
just do a single sided multiplication by
e to the I Theta
since complex numbers commute we can
also write this as a double-sided
transformation with e to the positive I
Theta over 2 on both sides
so why do the signs look different in
Clifford algebras
the key is to realize that in the X Y
plane the complex I is just the
bi-vector sigma x times Sigma Y in
disguise
in the complex number approach both the
Rotator and the object being rotated are
a scalar plus a bi vector
in Clifford algebras the object being
rotated is a vector instead
we can make the two equivalent if we
pre-multiply this vector by Sigma X
this explains where the sign change
comes from swapping order with a sigma X
introduces an extra minus sign
now let's look at the rotations in
four-dimensional space time with cl13 in
space time we should be able to do three
rotations as well as three lorentz
boosts
the rotations here work the same way as
in 3D space if we want to rotate in the
X Y plane we just use the cosine and
sine formulas using the bi-vector gamma
X gamma Y which squares to negative one
since this bi Vector squares 2 negative
one we can also use the exponential
formulas that we discussed previously
but what if we use a bi-vector that
involves the time basis Vector gamma T
what happens if we try to do a rotation
where the bi-vector involves the time
basis vector and one of the space basis
vectors
if you guessed lorentz boosts you are
correct
these three bifectors involving the time
basis Vector give us lorentz boosts in
the three orthogonal directions
but let's look at this exponential
formula more closely gamma T times gamma
X actually squares two plus one not
negative one
flipping the inner terms gives us a
negative sign but this cancels what the
negative sign we get when gamma X
squares 2 negative one and since gamma T
squares two plus one the answer is plus
one
so what happens when we take the
exponential of a symbol that squares two
plus one we can check this using the
split complex number J from the last
video where J squares two plus one
when we write out the infinite Taylor
series of e to the J Phi the zeroth
power goes to one the first Power gets J
in front the second power gets J squared
which is plus one the third power gets J
cubed which is just plus one times J and
the fourth power gets J squared twice
which is just plus one
this pattern of one J One J continues
forever notice that all the signs are
positive this time
if we separate the terms without Js from
the terms with JS the terms without J's
give us the Taylor series for hyperbolic
cosine and the terms with J's give us
the Taylor series for hyperbolic sign
as discussed in video 9 lorentz boosts
are just another word for hyperbolic
rotations so this result is indeed a
lorentz boost
if we replace the symbol J with the
bi-vector gamma T times gamma Z which
also squares two plus one we get a
similar formula involving hyperbolic
trig functions which represents a
lorentz boost in the Z Direction
we can get similar formulas for boosting
in the X and Y directions
it also turns out that putting a
negative sign in the hyperbolic angle
gives us the same formula but with a
negative sign in front of the sine H
term
so we can also rewrite the lorentz Boost
formula using exponentials
a boost in the eye direction is given by
exponentiating a bi-vector formed with
gamma T and Gamma I
more generally a boost is performed by
exponentiating a unit by Vector that
squares two plus one
to get this unit by Vector one axis must
be time like and the other must be
space-like and the Boost is done in the
spatial Direction contained in the
bi-vector
the angle Phi over 2 scales the size of
the bi Vector that's required for doing
a boost by a hyperbolic angle of Phi
now bi-vectors can be used for both
boosts and rotations so how can we tell
which bi-vectors do what
if a bi Vector squares to a positive
number it performs a boost since the
exponential gives us a hyperbolic
rotation similar to the split complex
number J
if a bi Vector squares to a negative
number its exponential performs a
circular rotation similar to the complex
number I
before moving on I'd like to say a few
things about how boosts are visualized
as a pair of reflections
you might think that a boost in the X
direction is given by reflection along X
and then a reflection along t
but this changes a future pointing
Vector into a past pointing Vector which
doesn't make sense for a boost
it's actually impossible to end up with
such a transformation using our boost
formula because hyperbolic cosine never
gives zero
if we rearrange this formula we see that
a boost is given by two reflections with
two time-like vectors
since hyperbolic cosine is always larger
in size than hyperbolic sine we know for
sure this Vector I'm labeling as Delta
is a time like vector
so a boost is given by two time-like
Reflections one reflects us into the
past light cone and another reflects us
back into the future light cone with the
Boost's hyperbolic angle being twice the
angle between the two time-like vectors
as a very quick aside when we have a
symbol Epsilon that squares to zero we
get the dual numbers
and these can be used to do Galilean
boosts from Galilean relativity you can
pause if you want to look at the details
but the Matrix representation of Epsilon
helps us build a Galilean Matrix that
changes coordinate frames according to
Galilean relativity we can do
double-sided Transformations that
perform a Galilean boosts which can also
be written with exponentials
so using Clifford algebras we've
discovered how to do rotations in 3D
space and also how to do rotations and
boosts in four-dimensional space time
and it's not difficult to see how we can
generalize these formulas to any
arbitrary dimension
in any Dimension if we want to rotate in
a plane we just take a bivector of size
1 in that plane and exponentiate it and
apply this double-sided transformation
with half angles
the members of Clifford algebras that do
these rotations using double-sided
Transformations are part of that
Clifford algebra's spin group
for example the exponentials that do
rotations in cl30 are part of the group
spin three zero and the exponentials
that do rotations and boosts in cl13 are
part of the group spin 1 3.
generally speaking the members that do
double-sided rotations in clpq are part
of the group spin PQ
but what is the formal definition of
these spin groups
we'll start by defining the spin and
group which lives inside the Clifford
algebra cln which has n basis vectors
that square two plus one and
anti-commute with each other
we already know the formula for
reflecting a vector v in the Clifford
algebra cln we just negative conjugate
it with a reflection Vector U
If U happens to be a unit Vector that
squares two plus one then U is its own
inverse and we can forget about the
inverse operation
however if U is not unit length then it
squares to its squared length and so U
inverse equals U over its squared length
this forces both copies of U to be
normalized by its length giving a
formula that does involve unit vectors
in this scenario we call you averser of
length one
next we learned that a rotation is just
a pair of Reflections so we can rotate
by doing two reflections with U2 and U1
the negative signs cancel and we know
the product of inverses is just the
inverse of the product in the reverse
order here I'll call U1 U2 averser of
length 2.
if U1 and U2 are unit vectors that
square two plus one then they each equal
their own inverses so the inverse of U1
U2 is just the reverse U2 U1 this is
sometimes denoted with a tilde or a
dagger
so we can write to the rotation formula
like this
however if U1 and U2 are not unit length
then multiplying by the reverse doesn't
give one instead it gives the product of
the squared lengths of the vectors
the inverse is then the reverse divided
by the squared lengths as before these
squared lengths normalize the vectors so
that they have length one
if we do three reflections with u3 U2 U1
this equals a rotation plus a reflection
only two of the negative signs cancel
and so we end up with a negative out in
front
here we have a verser of length 3.
again if all of these are unit vectors
we can write the inverse as just the
reverse
but for non-unit vectors the inverse
requires division by the squared
magnitudes so that the vectors become
normalized
if we do four Reflections this equals a
pair of rotations which combine together
to just give another rotation
we get no negative sign in front and
averser of length four
the rules for inverse are the same as
before
and we can keep going with larger and
larger reversers
so the rule is if we have a versa with
an odd length then we get a reflected
rotation and our formula requires a
minus sign in front
if we have a verser with an even length
we get a pure rotation and our formula
has no minus sign
one issue with these formulas is that
there's an infinite number of versers
that do the same transformation
for example reflecting along U 2u 5u and
100u all do the same thing
we can reduce this infinite number of
choices if we force the vector U to have
unit length in this case there are only
two vectors that can do the same
reflection plus u and minus U
since the transformation is double-sided
the two minus signs in minus U will
cancel out so it gives the same
transformation as plus u
the same is true for rotations if we
force the verser U1 U2 to be made up of
unit vectors then there are only two
choices of Versa that perform a given
rotation the plus and minus versions of
U1 U2
this extends for verses of any length if
the verser is built using only unit
vectors there are only two verses that
will do the same geometric
transformation the plus and minus signs
of the same versa
also to get the inverse of versers made
up of only unit length vectors we just
take the reverse
we say that the set of verses of even
length that are made up of unit vectors
is called the spin and group this
contains all possible rotations that can
be done in n-dimensional space
spin n is the double cover of the
rotation Matrix Group son which is the
special orthogonal n by n matrices
we say spin n is the double cover
because there are two members of spin n
that perform the same rotation as a
given son Matrix because positive and
negative versions of averser do the same
rotation they are both associated with a
single rotation Matrix
if we expand the set to include all
verses of both even and odd lengths made
up of unit vectors we call this the pin
and group this contains all possible
rotations and reflected rotations that
can be done in n-dimensional space
pin n is the double cover of the
orthogonal group O N which includes
rotations and reflected rotations again
it's the double cover because there are
two verses in the pin and group for
every on Matrix that performs the same
geometric operation
the plus and minus versions of the same
Versa perform the same geometric
operation
the reason we call it the pin and group
is a bit silly the son group does pure
rotations to include reflected rotations
we just cross off the S to get o n
similarly the spin and group does pure
rotations to include reflected rotations
we just cross off the S to get the pin
and group
one thing that's a bit awkward is that
we have two different formulas for
reflected rotations and pure rotations
one has a negative sign and the other
doesn't we can merge the two formulas
into a single formula if we introduce a
new operation called grade involution
for Clifford algebras which is usually
denoted by alpha or a hat symbol
the great Evolution just takes a vector
and gives it a negative sign
if you apply it to a product of vectors
then they each get the negative sign
if you apply it to a product of two
vectors then they each get a negative
sign which cancel with each other so
there is no overall sign change
in the case of three vectors two of them
cancel and there is an overall sign
change with four vectors all the minus
signs cancel and there is no sign change
the grade involution formula basically
swaps the signs of odd grade members and
leaves the sign unchanged for even grade
members
so by applying grade involution to the
first verser in a conjugation we
automatically get the correct sign
depending on if U is even grade or odd
grade
so this conjugation with a great
involution allows us to perform both
reflected rotations and pure rotations
in a Clifford algebra of any dimension
a conjugation that includes this grade
involution is sometimes called a twisted
conjugation
now we just need to put in a little more
work to generalize this to space-time in
a Clifford algebra clpq with p time
dimensions and Q space dimensions
as discussed previously the reflection
and rotation formulas work the exact
same as in physical space negative
conjugation with a vector for a
reflection and positive conjugation with
a grade 2 Versa for a rotation
we can Define the spin p q group almost
exactly as before even grade Versa is
made of unit vectors
however unit vectors include both time
like unit vectors that square two plus
one and space-like unit vectors that
square two minus one
this means that for members of the spin
PQ group an element multiplied by its
reverse won't always give plus one it
will sometimes give -1
for example if the transformation
contains a boost
sometimes we Define the spin plus p q
group to only include members who
multiply with their reverse to give plus
one and the minus one case is excluded
the pin p q group is simply defined as
all versars of any length made of unit
vectors
as expected spin PQ is the double cover
of so plus PQ where the plus indicates
that time Reflections are excluded and
pin PQ is the double cover of opq which
includes both space and time reflections
it's important to keep in mind that for
space time if a vector is space-like and
squares to a negative number then its
inverse will have an extra negative sign
so we always require these inverse
operations to get the signs right in our
equations
taking the inverse of a space like
vector requires dividing by the squared
length of the vector and this will give
us the extra required negative sign
so we've learned that we can transform a
vector v using Twisted conjugation with
averser r
it turns out that we can also transform
any general multi-vector M using a
similar transformation
let's start by assuming the verser r has
an even length and so the gradient
version doesn't change the sign
if m is made up of vectors v w x y we
can transform each individual Vector
using conjugation
the inner conjugation terms of R inverse
and R cancel with each other and we're
left with only the outer r's
so conjugating each individual Vector in
m is the same thing as conjugating M
itself
this allows us to transform bifector
planes tri-vector cubes and so on with
the same conjugation formula
the quaternions i j k can be written in
terms of bi vectors and rotated with the
standard conjugation formula just like a
vector
but now what if the verser r has any
lengths so its grade inversion can lead
to a plus sign or a minus sign depending
on its length
if we take the individual vectors that
make up M and twisted conjugate each one
we get a bunch of R's with grade
involution acting on them
one way to write great involution is to
take R times negative one to the power
of the length of R this way even length
R's get a plus sign and odd length R's
get a minus sign
if we have four grade involutions
multiplied together we get the same
result just taken to the fourth power
using exponent rules the exponent of an
exponent just gives multiplication of
the exponents
here the four is really the length of V
W X Y which is the length of M
so Twisted conjugation of a general
multi-vector M comes with an overall
sine s where the sign depends on both
the length of the multi-vector m and the
length of the verser r
I'm going to finish off this video with
a warning if you've been reading papers
or watching videos on geometric algebra
based on the work of a mathematician
named David hestonis you might have
heard people say that a spinner is
defined as any sum of even grade
elements in a Clifford algebra
this is not the definition of spinner
that I'm using in this video series I'm
defining Spinners as members of minimal
left ideals and Clifford algebras
these two definitions are different but
they are related I'll explain the
relationship between these two
definitions in future videos